Okay, now that you've understood some of the basics of autoimmunity, we're going to talk about a few specific disorders.
There are many disorders that are thought to be due to autoimmunity.
We'll cover some of them as we go through this course.
In this section, we're going to cover some of the prototypic disorders.
And the most classic disorder that's associated with autoimmunity is this first disorder,
which is called systemic lupus erythematosus, or also often known as simply lupus.
Now, this is a chronic disorder.
Once patients develop it, they essentially have it for the rest of their life.
It's a systemic disorder, which basically means that it involves multiple organ systems.
And, of course, it's autoimmune.
This disorder will be associated with flares and remissions.
So the patients will get a flare in which the symptoms will become worse.
And then that will remit.
And then over time, they'll develop another flare.
And then over time, they develop another flare.
And that's a common state of occurrence for patients with lupus.
It classically arises in a middle-aged female, as is relatively common with autoimmune disorders,
that demographic of middle-aged females.
And it is more common in African-Americans and Hispanics.
Now, I should note that it can occur in children, and it can also occur in older adults.
However, the female bias is less dramatic.
So, for example, if you look at individuals that are middle-aged who develop lupus,
for every ten females that develop lupus, one male will develop lupus.
Whereas, if you look at children and older adults, for every two females that develop lupus,
one male will develop lupus.
And so the female bias is less dramatic in children and adults.
That kind of makes sense, based on one of the principles that we talked about previously.
And that is that, remember, the notion of estrogen being somehow involved in autoimmunity.
And that estrogen, one thing that's been shown is that estrogen reduces the apoptosis of self-reactive B cells.
And so, for example, we know that middle-aged females would have a lot of estrogen floating around.
And so that would increase the risk for females.
Whereas, when you look at children and you look at older adults,
children would have less of an estrogen differential between males and females.
And older adults, as well, would have a less differential of estrogen between males and females.
And so perhaps that helps to explain why there's less of a female bias in that particular age group.
Now, if I were to summarize this disorder,
I would say that this is a disorder in which antigen-antibody complexes deposit in multiple tissues.
This then results in the activation of complement, which then damages those tissues.
So essentially, because this involves antigen-antibody complexes,
this is a type 3 hypersensitivity reaction.
In addition, because complement gets activated,
we end up using the complement factors that are present within our blood.
And so the patients will have a decreased CH50.
CH50 is a test which looks at the function of the patient's complement.
And it particularly looks at C1 all the way through C9
and tests the ability of the patient's complement to be able to life-spread blood cells.
And so if there's a decrease in the CH50,
it indicates that complement components are being used.
The patient's C3 and C4 levels will also be decreased.
And that's because they're using complement components as tissues are getting damaged.
The last point that I'll make is that the antibodies that are generated in this particular disorder
are directed against host nuclear material.
So again, we have antibodies against host nuclear material,
which eventually result in antibody-antigen complexes,
which will then deposit in those tissues, activate complement,
and eventually cause tissue damage.
Now let's go back to the whiteboard to understand a little bit about the pathogenesis of this disorder.
So what's currently thought is that, for example, if this is the epidermis of the skin,
and what I'm drawing here, each square represents a keratinocyte.
Imagine if UV light comes from the outside and hits the keratinocytes of the skin.
It'll damage some DNA.
And as it damages DNA, that can result in apoptosis of some of the cells.
So let's assume that a cell undergoes apoptosis.
You already know that when cells undergo apoptosis, the cytoplasm shrinks, the nucleus also shrinks,
and eventually little apoptotic bodies are released,
and this apoptotic debris is eventually taken up by macrophages.
Now let's assume that there is some decreased clearance or poor clearance of this apoptotic debris.
Now as apoptotic debris hangs around for a little bit longer,
for example, a self-reactive B lymphocyte may get exposed to that apoptotic debris,
hence it would see nuclear material.
And when it sees nuclear material, it would then begin to produce antibody versus nuclear antigens.
So as antibodies produced against nuclear antigens,
the next time UVV light hits the keratinocyte and causes apoptosis again,
which then results in release of nuclear material,
the antibody could bind this nuclear material,
and now you're going to have antigen-antibody complexes at low levels.
Now these antigen-antibody complexes can be taken up by dendritic cells.
So let's say this is a dendritic cell.
And once they're taken up by dendritic cells,
the antigen, which is nuclear material,
can actually activate the toll-like receptors present within dendritic cells.
These toll-like receptors, once activated, will then amplify the immune response.
And when they amplify the immune response, they'll further activate these B cells.
As they further activate the B cells, there'll be additional antibody produced.
And as additional antibodies produced, now we will have high levels of antigen-antibody complexes forming
the next time that there is apoptosis of a keratinocyte, for example.
These high levels of antigen-antibody complexes can enter into the blood, for example,
and then deposit in multiple tissues.
And as they deposit in multiple tissues, they can result in the activation of complement,
which can then damage tissues.
And so this is the current sort of paradigm of how patients might develop lupus.
One of the observations that helps to support this theory of pathogenesis
is the fact that patients with early complement deficiency have an increased risk of developing lupus.
In order to understand this, remember that the disorder is a problem of the formation of antibodies
against host nuclear material.
So here's your host nuclear material.
And when you have these antigen-antibody complexes, complement is essential for clearing antigen-antibody complexes.
For example, when you have antibody bound to antigen, in this particular case, this would be IgG,
then C1 will attach, and when C1 attaches, eventually C4 will come by, and C4 will be cleaved.
And when C4 is cleaved, eventually C2 will attach, and C2 will be cleaved.
And when you have the C1-Q-C2-C4 complex, that's also a C3 convertase.
So that would form a C3 convertase.
And the C3 convertase, of course, would take C3, and would cleave it to C3A and C3B.
And C3B, remember, is an important opsonin.
So as C3B begins to attach to this complex, it would act as an opsonin,
which would then allow for removal of this antigen-antibody complex.
For example, macrophages have the ability to recognize C3B and will use it as a means to take up this antigen-antibody complex.
Similarly, if the antigen-antibody complex is in the blood, erythrocytes have a receptor on them, which is called CR1.
And CR1 has the ability to bind C3B.
Now, when this binds to the antigen-antibody complex, it will take the antigen-antibody complex to the spleen,
and in the spleen, the macrophages will then eat and remove the antigen-antibody complex.
So essentially, what we need to recognize is that complement is necessary.
In particular, the early complement components of the classical pathway are necessary to remove and clear antigen-antibody complexes.
And so it wouldn't be too hard to imagine that if we had a deficiency of these early complement proteins,
that we would have an increased risk of developing lupus.
And in fact, patients with deficiency of early complement proteins, half of them will develop lupus.
And the most common complement deficiency to arise among these three would be a deficiency of C2.
And so these are some things that you should be aware of concerning early complement deficiency and its association with lupus.
Clinically, patients with lupus will have a whole bunch of findings.
And I know that sometimes students have difficulty remembering these, but if you put them together, it's not too difficult.
So first, let's start with a few of the nonspecific findings.
So the patients are going to have fever, they're going to have weight loss, and they're going to have fatigue.
And I don't think that's too difficult to remember, because anybody who's got activation of the immune system is going to have fever, weight loss, and fatigue.
Similarly, they're going to have lymphadenopathy, where there will be expansion of the lymph nodes, and the lymph nodes will become big.
And the reason the lymph nodes become big is, again, you've got activation of the immune system.
So all of these findings are nonspecific.
Although they're very common in patients with lupus, they don't help us to make a firm diagnosis of lupus, because they can be seen in many other disorders.
In addition, patients with lupus will also have something called Raynaud phenomena, and that's a circumstance where patients get arteriovasal spasm so that you can see this change in color, usually in their fingertips or on the tip of their nose, for example, where it changes from white to blue to red.
If you want to understand Raynaud, just press on your fingertip, and you'll notice that it turns white.
If you were to cut the blood supply for long enough, it would turn blue.
And when you would release the vasoconstriction and the blood would come back in, it would again turn red.
And simply press down on your finger, it turns white, release your finger, and you'll see that it turns red.
So that's the exact sequence that occurs in Raynaud's.
There's a vasospasm of the artery, which kind of cuts the blood supply for a few minutes, and that then turns the finger white.
Over time, as there's ischemia, it turns blue.
And then eventually, when the vasospasm releases, the red color comes back into the organ.
In particular, the fingertips or the nose.
And this is often associated with cold or with stress, meaning patients will get this white to blue to red change when there is cold temperature or when they're undergoing stress.
Raynaud phenomena is very nonspecific.
It can be seen in patients who have no autoimmune disorders.
In fact, when patients have Raynaud's, they often don't have any other autoimmune disorder.
Or it can be seen in association with multiple autoimmune disorders.
So, again, I put that in the nonspecific list.
What would be a little more specific for lupus is a malar butterfly rash or a discoid rash, especially on exposure to sunlight.
The malar butterfly rash is a rash that's seen over the cheekbones.
And here is an image of such a malar butterfly rash.
So it's called a butterfly rash because of this pattern here.
And, of course, this is seen over the cheekbones.
And so that's a classic rash that can occur in patients, especially when they are exposed to sunlight.
So that's a feature of lupus that you should be aware of.
Now, again, one feature does not make lupus.
And malar butterfly rash can be seen in other disorders as well.
However, it is an important diagnostic criteria for this particular disorder.
Another type of rash that can be seen is something called the discoid rash.
This is a rash which is circular and erythematous with scaling that can scar.
In fact, here's a picture of a discoid rash.
And you can see this kind of looks like a circular or disc-like rash.
You can see that it is erythematous.
You can see that there is scaling on this rash.
And over time, this would scar.
It's this type of rash that actually led to the name lupus.
Lupus literally means wolf.
And it was thought that this disorder arose when a person was bit by a wolf in the middle of the night.
And so they would get these lesions that would scar.
And so people would call this lupus because they thought that this was due to a wolf bite.
And so it is important to be aware of this classic lesion.
And this is also one of the diagnostic criteria as well.
So a malar rash or a discoid rash, especially upon exposure to sunlight.
Now, there are 11 official criteria for lupus.
And of those 11, number 1 is a malar rash, number 2 is a discoid rash,
and number 3 is a rash upon exposure to sunlight.
So 1, 2, and 3 are taken care of right there.
Now, I should take a moment to just be clear that although we're going to list 11 criteria,
not all criteria are going to be seen in any particular patient.
In fact, you only need 4 of these criteria, or at least 4 of these criteria,
in order to make a diagnosis of lupus.
Other features that can be seen are oral or nasopharyngeal ulcers.
In fact, this is the fourth criteria.
Arthritis, when patients get arthritis, this usually involves peripheral joints,
usually two or more joints.
The joints will be tender and swelling, but there will be no deformity.
And that is number 5 criteria.
Number 6 criteria is that patients get inflammation of the serosal surfaces.
So, for example, they'll get inflammation of the serosa of the lung,
giving them pleuritis.
And that can result in pleuritic pain.
So when patients breathe in, they might feel pain.
Or it could result in a rub that could be heard on auscultation.
Similarly, the patients could get inflammation of the serosal surface of the heart.
That would give them pericarditis.
And that could be detected by EKG.
Or it could be detected by auscultating a rub.
Or it could be detected by an effusion in the pericardium.
So, this is a criteria as well.
And serositis is a common finding in lupus.
The seventh criteria is CNS problems, in particular psychosis or seizures.
The eighth, so that's the seventh problem.
The eighth criteria is that patients will often have renal damage.
Now, this criteria is particularly important, so I want to spend a moment discussing it.
Renal damage in lupus can be that the patients get something called a nephritic syndrome,
which is going to be characterized by hypertension and hematuria.
They can also get a type of disorder in the kidney, which is called nephrotic syndrome,
which is going to be characterized by high levels of protein leaking out into the urine.
They could get both a combination of nephritic and nephrotic syndrome.
They could have no damage to the kidney.
Damage to the kidney is not always necessary in lupus.
And so, there's a wide spectrum of damage that can occur within the kidney.
But the kidney is very important because it's a common cause of death in patients with lupus,
and so you do need to be aware of what can happen in the kidney.
The highest yield points concerning renal damage are the following.
The first is that the most common and most severe problem that the patients can have in the kidney
is called diffuse proliferative glomerulonephritis.
And this is a type of nephritic syndrome.
We'll talk more about nephritic syndrome when you do the renal section,
but you should just bury in the back of your brain that this is a type of nephritic syndrome.
Another high yield point is that patients who have proteinuria and nephrotic syndrome,
and again, you'll cover nephrotic syndrome when we do the renal section,
will have a type of damage in the kidney called membranous glomerulonephritis.
So, this is criteria number seven, this being six.
The eighth criteria is that the patients will develop antibodies against red blood cells,
or white blood cells, or platelets, basically some cell within the blood.
And as they develop antibodies against those cells, they'll begin to damage those cells,
and so if it's red cells, they'll get an anemia.
If it's platelets, they'll get a thrombocytopenia.
And if, for example, it's white cells, such as neutrophils or lymphocytes, they'll get a leukopenia.
And so, this is an important finding in lupus patients.
And now, I'd like to make one important point here,
and that is this finding is going to be due to a type 2 hypersensitivity reaction.
Remember that, in general, lupus is a type 3 hypersensitivity reaction
where antibody and antigen complexes will deposit in multiple tissues.
However, in patients who have lupus who develop this problem in their blood,
generally what happens is they have a direct antibody against the red cell, for example,
and that then results in destruction of the red cell.
And so, that's a type 2 hypersensitivity.
Another feature that can be found in patients with lupus is something called Liebman-Sachs endocarditis.
And the first thing that I'd like to say is that lupus can affect any layer of the heart.
So, for example, lupus can affect the pericardium, and that would give you pericarditis,
and we've already talked about that.
Lupus can affect the myocardium, giving you myocarditis,
and lupus can also affect the endocardium, giving you a Liebman-Sachs endocarditis.
Now, a key finding of Liebman-Sachs endocarditis is that patients get small vegetations
on both sides of the mitral valve.
And, again, this is a historically classic finding,
but it's now rarely seen due to treatment with immunosuppressives.
Now, when patients normally get endocarditis,
let's imagine that this is a picture of the heart, and this is the mitral valve here,
they would get vegetations on the valve, but those vegetations would be on one side of the valve.
In Liebman-Sachs endocarditis, you get vegetations,
and there's small little vegetations that are present on both sides of the valve.
And so this is an important finding that is classic for patients with lupus,
but, again, is not really seen because of the fact that we now treat with immunosuppressives.
But it is something to be aware of.
It is not one of the diagnostic criteria, but, again, something that you should be aware of.
And so on this slide, we've added an additional three criteria, correct?
Seven, eight, and nine.
The tenth criteria is that patients who have lupus will often have an antinuclear antibody.
Now, the antinuclear antibody is an antibody that would be present in the serum of the patient,
and it is good for screening because it is relatively sensitive.
However, it is nonspecific.
And why we say it's nonspecific?
Because, first of all, antinuclear antibodies can be seen in 5% of normal individuals,
and also antinuclear antibodies can be seen in many autoimmune disorders.
So, again, it's sensitive that there might be something going on.
However, it's nonspecific.
So that's criteria number 10.
Criteria number 11 is that you have some antibody beyond the antinuclear antibody.
So, for example, patients can have an anti-double-stranded DNA antibody or an anti-Smith antibody.
And the anti-double-stranded DNA and anti-Smith antibodies are very specific for lupus.
And so this is something to be aware of.
Again, anti-double-stranded DNA and anti-Smith antibodies are specific.
So let's say a patient had a positive ANA.
The next thing we would do, we might test for anti-double-stranded DNA and anti-Smith if we were worried about lupus.
Another point that I would like to make that can show up on examinations is that the anti-double-stranded DNA antibody
is associated with disease activity, and it is also associated with renal nephritis.
And so this antibody can be somewhat prognostic and can also be used to follow disease activity.
For example, if we're worried about a patient developing a relapse, we could test the anti-double-stranded DNA antibody,
and if the titers are high, then we could suggest that the patient is about to relapse and perhaps we might treat.
So anyway, the anti-double-stranded DNA antibody is associated with both prognosis as well as active disease.
Another potential antibody that can be seen in patients with lupus is something called an anti-phospholipid antibody,
and this also forms part of the 11th criteria.
So remember the 10th criteria is the presence of an anti-nuclear antibody.
The 11th criteria is the presence of an anti-double-stranded DNA antibody, anti-Smith antibody, or an anti-phospholipid antibody.
Now anti-phospholipid antibodies are antibodies that bind proteins when those proteins are bound to phospholipids.
What happens is when the protein is bound to phospholipids, the epitopes are revealed that are antigenic,
and that then results in an anti-phospholipid antibody.
There are three anti-phospholipid antibodies that are commonly tested clinically.
The first is anti-cardiolipin antibody, the second is lupus anticoagulant,
and the third is an antibody called anti-beta-2-glycoprotein-1.
The anti-cardiolipid antibody is particularly interesting because it can produce a false positive screening test for syphilis.
Now recall that when we screen for syphilis, we use one of two tests, the VDRL or the RPR,
and these tests are actually looking for the presence of anti-cardiolipid antibodies.
In fact, when patients get infected with syphilis, that results in tissue damage, lipids are released,
and it's common for patients with syphilis to develop anti-cardiolipid antibodies.
And so these two tests actually have cardiolipid as a reagent, and they look for anti-cardiolipid antibodies.
Now let's imagine that a patient has lupus and generates anti-cardiolipid antibodies.
They, of course, could turn this test positive,
and so you would have a false positive reaction in the two screening tests for syphilis.
Now, of course, patients with lupus can also get infected and get syphilis,
and so if you wanted to confirm, you could confirm using the direct or the specific treponemal tests,
and so, for example, one test would be the FTA-ABS test that could be used to confirm any positive screening test for syphilis.
Another important point concerning anti-phospholipid antibodies is that patients can have an anti-phospholipid antibody called lupus anticoagulant.
This anti-phospholipid antibody falsely elevates the patient's PTT test
because it interferes with the phospholipids that are used in the PTT test,
and so these patients will have a falsely elevated PTT.
Now what's interesting about these patients with lupus anticoagulant
is that those patients can also have an associated syndrome called the anti-phospholipid antibody syndrome.
Anti-phospholipid antibody syndrome is a syndrome where the patients have an anti-phospholipid antibody,
usually lupus anticoagulant, plus a hypercoagulable state.
Now when they have this hypercoagulable state, what happens is the patients can get arterial and venous thrombosis.
So, for example, they can get DVTs, they can get hepatic vein thrombosis,
they could get placental thrombosis, which would result in recurrent pregnancy loss,
they could get cerebral thrombosis, which would result in stroke,
and all of these are associated with this anti-phospholipid antibody.
Now, although the anti-phospholipid antibody interferes with the PTT test
and causes the PTT to increase, it's interesting, that's paradoxical,
because actually the patients have a hypercoagulable state,
so that's one thing to be aware of.
Another thing to be aware of is that these patients will then require lifelong anticoagulation.
Now I'd like to say one more thing about the anti-phospholipid antibody syndrome.
It is associated with lupus, however, it more commonly occurs as a primary disorder.
So a patient can have anti-phospholipid antibodies with all the problems that I just stated,
causing the anti-phospholipid antibody syndrome, and doesn't have to have lupus.
In fact, more commonly, they wouldn't have lupus.
The last point that I'd like to make concerning antibodies is that patients that get drug-induced lupus
often have an antibody called an antihistone antibody.
So let's take a step back.
First of all, there are a subset of drugs that can induce lupus,
and the classic drugs to be aware of are hydralazine, procainamide, and isoniazid.
These can induce lupus.
When patients get drug-induced lupus, they will have a positive ANA, anti-nuclear antibody,
and then that ANA will be specific to antihistone antibodies.
So you would test for antihistone antibodies, and the antihistone antibody would be positive.
Now, some other features of drug-induced lupus is that the patients will develop rash,
serositis, and hematologic problems.
However, CNS and renal involvement is rare with drug-induced lupus.
And finally, the last point is that if you remove the drug,
this will usually result in remission of the drug-induced lupus.
Treatment for lupus is that patients should avoid sunlight.
Again, the whole notion that sunlight is damaging DNA, resulting in apoptosis,
resulting in antigen-antibody complexes.
So one thing would be to avoid sunlight.
If the patient undergoes a flare, we could give glucocorticoids.
Of course, what's driving the entire process is the immune system,
and so if you give glucocorticoids, you'd suppress the immune system.
And if the patients have refractory disease or if the patients have severe disease,
other immunosuppressive agents can be used.
Now, with this treatment, the prognosis is fairly good.
There is a greater than 90% five-year survival.
This is important because in the 1950s, the five-year survival was less than 50%.
So treatment has certainly helped the five-year survival.
Renal failure and infection are the most common causes of death.
Renal failure, we've talked about the importance of renal involvement in lupus.
And infection, there's kind of two ways by which patients could get infection.
Number one, we're treating the patients with immunosuppressives,
so that could result in infection.
And number two, remember that patients can generate antibodies to their white cells,
and so if they damage the white cells, that would increase the risk of infection as well.
So renal failure and infection are the most common causes of death.
Again, I'll remind you of two high-yield points here.
Patients who have nephritic syndrome will have a diffuse proliferative glomerulonephritis.
Patients who have nephrotic syndrome will have membranous nephropathy.
That often shows up on exams.
And then the final point is that if patients do survive late,
then one of the common causes of death or increasingly common causes of death
is accelerated coronary atherosclerosis.
So these patients tend to have a coronary atherosclerosis that is accelerated for their age,
which can also result in death,
especially if they manage to avoid renal failure and infection as causes of death.
The second disorder that we're going to discuss is called Sjövren syndrome.
This is characterized by autoimmune destruction of the lacrimal glands and the salivary glands.
The autoimmune destruction is mediated by lymphocytes,
and so it is an example of a type 4 hypersensitivity reaction.
Patients who have Sjövren syndrome will classically present with dry eyes
because of the destruction of the lacrimal glands.
They will present with dry mouth because of the destruction of the salivary glands.
And in addition, patients can also complain or have the feature of recurrent dental caries.
This is because, recall, that the salivary gland is normally producing fluid,
and that fluid will wash over the surface of the teeth,
and it will maintain some degree of cleanliness.
However, if we lose the salivary glands,
then that would increase the risk of development of dental caries.
Women usually present at an older age, so it's classically an older woman,
and they might complain of not being able to chew a cracker,
and that's, again, because you need the secretions of the salivary gland
to add the moisture to the cracker.
And they also might complain of a feeling of dirt in their eyes,
and that's because the lacrimal glands are constantly pushing fluid over the surface of the eye,
which helps to wash away any dirt that might come into the eye from the outside environment.
So these patients obviously don't have their lacrimal glands,
and so they might get the experience of feeling dirt in their eyes.
Now, although the classic presentation is that of dry eyes and dry mouth,
it's important to recognize that patients can also have extra glandular manifestations.
So, for example, patients can have joint problems, CNS problems, skin problems, etc.
When patients have Sjövren's syndrome, it could be primary,
or it can be associated with another autoimmune disorder.
It's very common for Sjövren's to be associated with another autoimmune disorder.
However, there's a whole variety of autoimmune disorders that can be associated with Sjövren's.
However, the most common is rheumatoid arthritis,
and so that's an important high-yield point to be aware of.
Patients who have Sjövren's syndrome will often have something in their blood called rheumatoid factor.
This is usually seen in rheumatoid arthritis.
However, it can also be seen in patients with Sjövren's syndrome,
and it's one more of those associations to be aware of.
Now, what's interesting about rheumatoid factor is that if the patient had rheumatoid arthritis,
you would expect rheumatoid factor.
However, even if the patient doesn't have rheumatoid arthritis, meaning they have primary Sjövren's syndrome,
they often also have rheumatoid factor in their blood.
And so this is something that some people have recognized as a diagnostic criteria,
i.e. the presence of rheumatoid factor in the blood.
Patients who have Sjövren's syndrome will have an ANA, or an antinuclear antibody,
and in particular, they will have antibodies against ribonucleoproteins.
Ribonucleoproteins are structures that are comprised of RNA and proteins.
So, for example, the ribosomes are an example of ribonucleoproteins,
and patients will often have antiribonucleoprotein antibodies.
In particular, the two that they classically have is anti-SSA and anti-SSB.
Now, there's no rocket science here.
SS indicates that this is Sjövren's syndrome,
and the A represents the A antibody, and the B represents the B antibody.
So no one's ever going to ask you whether SSA and SSB are associated with Sjövren's
because the name kind of gives it away.
However, what you should be aware of regarding SSA and SSB
is that, first of all, the epitopes are ribonucleoproteins.
So SSA and SSB are antiribonucleoprotein antibodies, number one.
Number two, patients who have SSA and SSB will often have extra-glandular manifestations.
And number three, and perhaps the most high yield, is that patients who have SSA and SSB,
the SSA in particular can cross the placenta if the patient's pregnant and can attack the baby or the fetus.
And so these babies can develop neonatal lupus.
Neonatal lupus is characterized by rash and hepatitis and thrombocytopenia and anemia.
But most important, one of the key complications of neonatal lupus is congenital heart block.
And so this is a high yield point that you want to take home.
The association of pregnancy and SSA with neonatal lupus and in particular congenital heart block.
Now interestingly, you can also see SSA and SSB in a subset of patients with lupus.
So there is a fairly significant subset of patients with lupus that can also have SSA and SSB.
And this is important because if they have SSA or SSB, they would again have the risk of neonatal lupus
and would again have the risk of congenital heart block.
So it's important when a patient has SLE and gets pregnant that we screen pregnant patients
to make sure that they don't have anti-SSA or anti-SSB.
And if they do, that we then watch for or recognize the risk for neonatal lupus
with the feared complication of congenital heart block.
There are some additional diagnostic criteria for Sjogren's syndrome.
Recognize that dry eyes and dry mouth can occur from other things other than Sjogren's syndrome.
In addition, SSA and SSB can be present due to other things other than Sjogren's syndrome.
So one of the important diagnostic criteria is that we can do a biopsy of the minor salivary glands.
What happens is we do a biopsy of the lip and we look at the minor salivary glands that are associated with the lip.
And we can look for the presence of lymphocytes that are attacking the minor salivary glands.
And that's called lymphocytic xylabinitis.
And that's an important diagnostic criteria to establish a diagnosis of Sjogren's syndrome as well.
To highlight this important diagnostic criteria, I've included this image.
So on the left here is relatively normal tissue.
This is a lip biopsy from a patient with suspected Sjogren's syndrome.
And we, of course, have biopsied the minor salivary gland.
Now, when you look at this, you'll notice that you see a bunch of glandular-like structures.
Notice that some of the cells contain more pink cytoplasm.
And these represent the serous cells, which are producing a more watery fluid.
And other cells have a more abundant, clear cytoplasm.
And these cells represent the mucinous cells, which produce a mucus-like fluid.
The watery fluid and the mucus-like fluid will combine together to make saliva.
On the left, again, this is relatively normal.
When you move away from the left and you come to the center, you notice that there is this lymphocytic infiltrate,
which is destroying some of the salivary gland.
And so this would help us to make a diagnosis of Sjogren's syndrome.
The reason we do the biopsy is to exclude other causes of destruction of the salivary gland.
And so some of the things that we would want to exclude include, for example, amyloidosis.
So we would want to confirm that there's no amyloid deposition within the gland.
Similarly, we might also want to exclude a disease or a disorder called sarcoidosis,
which is essentially a disorder in which you get non-caseating granulomas in multiple organs throughout the body.
So it's important to remember that dry eyes and dry mouth can be due to other than Sjogren's syndrome,
and we need to exclude other causes of dry eyes and dry mouth.
And so a biopsy is particularly helpful.
So in the end, if you want to summarize Sjogren's syndrome,
there's essentially three major criteria that you need to look for in order to make a diagnosis.
The first is going to be the presence of dry eyes.
And when you think about dry eyes, we could test that clinically by looking for a decrease in tear production,
and there are some clinical tests that we can use to do that.
However, in the end, for your purposes, you should simply remember dry eyes criteria number one.
Criteria number two is an ANA plus SSA or SSB or rheumatoid factor.
And criteria number three is the presence of lymphocytic xyladenitis.
Now, in the end, you only really need two of the three diagnostic criteria to make a diagnosis.
However, I really wanted to emphasize the lymphocytic xyladenitis because it's a common board question
where patients will come in with dry eyes and dry mouth, but they won't have the other diagnostic criteria,
and you'll need to think about other disorders that could do that.
For example, amyloidosis or sarcoidosis or drugs or prior radiation, etc.
And so remember, the three important diagnostic criteria and the fact that we need two out of those three
in order to make a diagnosis of Sjogren's syndrome.
One final point about Sjogren's syndrome is that there's an increased risk for B-cell lymphoma.
Now, patients with Sjogren's syndrome will normally have inflammation of the parotid glands,
and so the parotid glands will actually be enlarged, and so when you look at these patients,
both parotid glands are usually enlarged.
Now, let's say that there's a patient that has Sjogren's syndrome, and they've had it for 10 or 15 years,
and all of a sudden they show up where one of the parotid glands is becoming bigger than the other.
Well, when one becomes bigger than the other, then you'd have to think about what's causing that enlargement on one side.
And one of the things that can cause such an enlargement is B-cell lymphoma,
and so this is an important association to be aware of, especially late in the disease course.
The third disorder that we're going to talk about is systemic sclerosis.
This is an autoimmune disorder in which you get sclerosis of the skin and visceral organs.
Sclerosis simply means hardening of tissue, and in this particular disorder,
the reason that you get hardening of tissue is because there's deposition of collagen within tissues.
Of course, fibroblasts are the cells that deposit collagen,
and so the underlying problem in this disorder is that the fibroblasts get activated,
and they deposit collagen within multiple tissues.
Concerning the pathogenesis, one theory is that in this particular disorder,
you have an immune reaction against mesenchymal antigen, some unknown mesenchymal antigen,
and so what I've drawn here is the blood vessel.
These are endothelial cells, and underneath here is the connective tissue.
So imagine that we have an immune reaction against an antigen within the connective tissue,
or it might even be the endothelial cell itself.
When we get this immune reaction, that results in a dysfunction of the endothelial cells.
When we get dysfunction of the endothelial cells, there's increased expression of adhesion molecules.
This then allows inflammatory cells to come into the connective tissue.
Another problem that occurs is that there's going to be increased expression of a molecule called endothelion.
Endothelion. Endothelion is an extremely strong vasoconstrictor, and that would result in constriction of the vessel.
In addition, there would be decrease in the production of nitric oxide, and nitric oxide is a vasodilator.
So in balance, we're going to have vasoconstriction.
And then finally, the third thing that will happen is that the endothelial cells will begin to produce platelet-derived growth factor and TGF-beta.
Now, TGF-beta and platelet-derived growth factor both have the ability to activate fibroblasts and to cause fibrosis.
And so this will then result in fibrosis around the blood vessel.
And over time, especially with the vasoconstriction, you'll get ischemia, and then that ischemia will result in additional fibrosis.
And so as we get continued fibrosis, we eventually get end-organ damage, which then results in systemic sclerosis.
Systemic sclerosis can be divided into two types.
There is a limited type and a diffuse type.
In the limited type, there is limited skin involvement with late visceral involvement.
The prototype of this subtype is called the Crest syndrome.
C stands for calcinosis.
Calcinosis means that the patients get deposition of calcium in subcutaneous connective tissues.
And the C also helps me to remember that the patients have an anti-centromere antibody.
The R stands for Raynaud phenomena, so these patients will often have Raynaud phenomena.
Again, remember that Raynaud phenomena, it usually occurs in the fingertips or the tip of the nose or the ear lobes, for example.
And it results when the patient's exposed to cold or stressed.
This then causes an arterial vasospasm, which then causes the tip of the finger, for example, to turn white and then eventually blue.
And then when the vasospasm releases, to become red again.
This is one of the earliest signs that it's seen in the limited type of systemic sclerosis.
It's often seen years before any other symptoms or signs develop.
But remember that Raynaud phenomena can also be seen in lupus patients.
It can also be seen in normal patients.
And so it's not specific for the disorder.
The E in the Crest stands for esophageal dysmotility.
Let's go back to the whiteboard to remind ourselves.
Here is the esophagus.
And then we have, of course, the esophagus feeding into the stomach.
And so what can happen in these patients is that they can get fibrosis of the wall of the lower portion of the esophagus.
That would result in dysmotility.
And perhaps the patients could even have difficulty swallowing both solids and liquids.
The reason for both solids and liquids is because we require peristalsis to bring down both solids and liquids.
And if this wall was fibrosed, we would not have the normal peristalsis of the esophageal tube.
In addition, because we get fibrosis in the lower portion of the esophagus, there can be disruption of the gastroesophageal junction.
And if there's disruption of this junction, there can be reflux of acid from the stomach back into the esophagus.
And so these patients can also have gastroesophageal reflux disease.
The S stands for sclerodactyly.
Sclerodactyly refers to fibrosis of the skin of the hands.
And in fact, that's what we mean by limited skin involvement, that it usually involves the skin of the hand.
Now, the fibrosis of the skin of the hand will make the skin tight.
And so you'll lose the wrinkles on the skin that is present on the surface of the fingers, for example.
And eventually, the tightness of the skin can even constrict the blood vessels so that the patients can get necrosis and ulceration of the fingertips.
And then finally, the T represents telangiectasias of the skin.
Telangiectasias are dilated capillaries, and this would result in red marks on the skin.
Now, although the limited type can be summarized by crest, some patients can develop more extensive internal organ involvement.
But overall, the prognosis is good.
A second type of systemic sclerosis is the diffuse type.
And in the diffuse type, you get diffuse involvement of skin with early visceral involvement.
Now, any organ can be involved.
Classic organs include vessels, giving you renal phenomena.
The most commonly involved organ system is the GI tract.
This can, for example, involve the stomach, leading to delayed emptying.
It can involve the small bowel, leading to malabsorption.
The esophagus is the classic site.
And when you get esophageal involvement, you get dysphagia.
You can also get another finding of gastroesophageal reflux disease, which you'll learn more about when you do your GI lectures.
The lung is also an important site of involvement.
Pulmonary involvement is the most common cause of death.
So you should know that the patients with this disorder, when it involves a lung, they can get interstitial fibrosis, or they can develop pulmonary hypertension.
The kidney is also an important organ that can be involved.
The kidney is the second most common cause of death.
The most feared complication of the kidney is called scleroderma renal crisis.
And this is when patients get sudden onset of acute renal failure and severe hypertension.
The good thing about this is that if you treat it with ACE inhibitors and you normalize the high blood pressure, that can lead to a resolution of the crisis.
And so that's an important thing to be aware of.
And then finally, patients can also get involvement of the heart.
And so they can, for example, get heart failure because of the pulmonary hypertension, or they may actually get fibrosis of the cardiac tissue itself.
So one important association to be aware of is that patients with the diffuse type will have antibodies against DNA topoisomerase 1.
So limited type, anti-centromary antibodies.
Diffuse type, DNA topoisomerase 1 antibodies.
Here's a picture of a hand of a patient with systemic sclerosis.
Notice here, and here, and here, that there are decreased wrinkles on the surface of the fingers.
In fact, if you look at your own fingers, you'll be able to recognize wrinkles.
But notice that there's a loss of wrinkles here.
And that's because there's a tightening of the skin because of the deposition of fibrosis within the skin, making the skin thick and hard.
And so you're not able to perceive these wrinkles.
Another important thing to recognize is that there's this lesion here on the thumb.
This so happens to be calcinosis.
There's calcium that has deposited in the connective tissue underneath the skin there.
And so this is an example.
In fact, this patient had the limited type of systemic sclerosis.
One important thing that I should mention here, the hand is commonly involved in both the limited and the diffuse type.
However, in the limited type, it would be limited to the hand, usually.
And in the diffuse type, it would involve the hand plus multiple other sites.
For example, the limbs, the chest, the abdomen, etc.
And so that would give you a clue that the patient actually may have diffuse scleroderma.
The final disorder that we're going to talk about is called mixed connective tissue disease.
This is an autoimmune disorder in which you get mixed features of lupus, systemic sclerosis, and polymyositis.
Polymyositis is a disorder that we're going to talk about later in this course.
So, for example, the patients can have arthritis, like you might see in a lupus patient.
They can have esophageal dysmotility with some gastroesophageal reflux disease, as you might see in a patient with systemic sclerosis.
And they can have myalgia with inflammation of the muscles or myositis, which you might see in a patient with polymyositis.
Now, what's interesting about this disorder is that the patients usually begin very non-specifically.
For example, they'll have fatigue, myalgia, low-grade fever, Raynaud.
These are the characteristic initial signs.
And so they won't really be placed into any particular connective tissue disorder.
Over time, they begin to develop overlapping features, for example, of lupus and systemic sclerosis and polymyositis, as I've already described.
And then that allows you to classify them as mixed connective tissue disease.
There are some hallmarks of the disorder.
For example, patients with MCTD or mixed connective tissue disease often have Raynaud's.
They usually lack severe renal involvement.
They usually lack severe CNS involvement.
They usually have very severe arthritis and severe pulmonary hypertension.
In fact, pulmonary hypertension is the major cause of death.
But the most important take-home and the highest yield is that patients with mixed connective tissue disease will have an ANA,
but they'll also have antibodies against U1 ribonucleoprotein.
And that is a very important take-home point.
So that concludes this section on more specific autoimmune disorders.